Meier mss., 1927-2010
Indiana University Digital Library Program
- Correspondence, 1927-2009, undated (Box 1)
  - Professional, 1982-2009, undated (Box 4)
    - General
      - E
        Engel, Angela, 2008 (Includes letters from Meier)
        Engel, Brenda, 1996
        Engel, Jeremy, CPESS teacher, undated
        ERIC, 1993
        Expeditionary Learning Outward Bound, 1994
      - F
        Featherstone, Joseph, undated (Letter from Meier)
        Feiman-Nemser, Sharon of Michigan State University, 1987
        Feldman, Sandra, President of the American Federation of Teachers, 1997-2004
        Fine, Michelle of the University of Pennsylvania, 1988
        Fitzgerald, Stephanie, 1996
        Ford, Terry N., 1995
        French-American Foundation, 1994-1995
        Fried, Robert, 1993-1995
        Fund for New York City Public Education, undated
        Furze, Suzanne of the Colorado Rocky Mountain School, 1988
      - G
        Gans, Herbert J. of Columbia University, 1993
        Gardner, Howard of Harvard University, 1995-2000
        Gates Foundation, 2001
        Gaving, Ayla, 2003
        Gephardt, Richard A., House of Representatives, Congress of the United States, 1997
        Gibboney, Richard A., of the University of Pennsylvania, 1996-2006 (Includes enclosures)
        Ginley, Mary of the City University of New York, 1998-1999
        Giorgi, Michael J., 1995
        Girls Incorporated, 1994-1995
        Gittell, Marilyn, 1994
        Getzendanner, Joel D., 1994 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Glickman, Carl, 2002
        Gold, Judith, undated
        Goldschmidt, Neil, Governor of Oregon, 1988
        Goldsmith-Conley, Elizabeth, 1994-2002
        Goodlad, John, 2003
        Gould, Ruth and Nathan Gould, 1995
        Grabelle, Sam of the Big Picture Company, 2004 (Includes foreword by Meier)
        Graczyk, Maryann L., President of the Mississippi American Federation of Teachers, 1988
        Graff, Gerald, 2002 (Includes enclosure)
        Graham, Peter, parent of CPE students, 1992
        Grant, Gerald, 1995
        Graubard, Allen, 1987-2000 (Includes enclosures)
        Great Neck Public Schools, 1995
        Greeley, Kathy, undated
        Greene, Maxine of Columbia University Teachers College, 1989-1998, undated
        Greenleaf, Phyllis, 2006
        Greenspan, Richard, 1988
        Gregorich, Patricia, 1996-1997, undated (Includes enclosure)
        Gribskov, Margaret, 1999
        Grinnell College, 2008 (Includes letters from Meier, enclosures)
        Guttman Foundation, 1995
      - H (Box 5)
        Hager, Sharp and Abramson, 1987
        Hagstrom, David, 2003
        Hale, Sara J., student, 1996
        Handlan, Raymond L., 1992
        Hargreaves, Andy of the Ontario Institute for Studies in Education, 1996
        Harman, Susan, 1994-1998, undated
        Hartman, Bruce, 2004
        Harvard Education Letter, 2005
        Harvard University, 1993-2000, undated (Includes enclosures) (Separate folder) (See also: Oversize 3, folder 8)
        Harwayne, Shelley, 2003
        Headmasters Association, 1994
        Heartland Area Education Agency, 1989
        Hebrew Union College, 1993-1995
        Hein, George E., 1991-1992
        Heinemann, 2000-2006
        Henderson, Haven, 1985
        Hernández, Máximo, 1993 (Includes enclosure)
        Hertel, Rosemary J., 2006
        Hilton Head Primary School, undated
        Hoffman, Berenice, 1992 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Hoffman, Marvin, 2008, undated (Includes draft by Meier)
        The Holmes Group, 1995
        Holmes Junior High School, 1996
        Holt Associates, 1994-1995
        Holtz, Arlene, 1996
        Holy Ghost Preparatory School, 1996
        Holzer, Matt, 1997
        Holzman, Michael of Libraries for the Future, 2000
        Hong, Loraine, 1995
        Hrycyna, Andrew, of Beacon Press, 2000-2005 (See also: Books; Mission Hill News photocopies from Andy Hrycyna)
        Hughes, Philip W., 2004-2005 (Includes enclosure)
        Hull, Bill, undated (Includes enclosure)
        Hull, Sara, 2001 (Includes enclosure)
        Hunt, Neen, 1994 (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier)
        Hutchinson, Kevin, 1996 (Includes letter from Meier)
      - I
        Illinois State Board of Education, 1995
        Independence School, New York, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        Institute for Democracy and Peace, 1994 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Institute for Development of Educational Activities, 1995
        Institute for Responsive Education, 1994-1995
        Institute for Secondary Education Parent-Teacher Association, 1995
        Institute for Student Achievement, 2004
        Instructor, 1987-1988
        The International Schools Partnership, 1995
        Isenberg, Jane, 1994
        Isom, John E., undated (Includes enclosure)
      - J
        Jewish Life Network, 1995 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Jews for Racial and Economic Justice, 1995 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Jones, Margot, 1994, undated
        Jordan, Charlene, 1997
        Josephson, William, 1985-1986 (Includes enclosure, letter from Meier)
        Jossey-Bass Publishers, 1994
      - K
        Kandler, Henry D., 1994
        Kaplan, Susan Adler, 1988
        Kassebaum, Nancy, Senator from Kansas, Congress of the United States, 1994, undated (Includes letter from Meier)
        Katz, Michael B., 1984 (Includes letters from Meier)
        Kaufman, Katie of Berryssa Union School District, 1995 (Includes enclosure, letter from Meier)
        Kay, Beth, 2004
        Kearns, David T. of the Xerox Corporation, 1997
        Kern, Jane, 1998 (Includes enclosure)
        Klinger, Nancy, 1996 (Includes enclosure)
        Kohn, Alfie, 1993-2002 (Includes enclosure)
        Kozol, Jonathan of the Phi Delta Kappan, 1992-2007 (Includes enclosures)
        Krinsky, Robert D. of the National Dance Institute, 1995
        Krovetz, Martin L. of San Jose State University, 1999
        Krupnick, Catherine of Harvard University, 1994
        Kunin, Madeleine M., Deputy Secretary of the U.S. Department of Education, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
      - L
        Lappe, Frances Moore, undated (Includes enclosures)
        Larson, Mark of Evanston Township High School, 1995-1997
        Lawrence High School Philips Academy, 1988
        Lawrence, Rayn of Chappaqua Public Schools, 1987
        Lehman College, 1995
        Levine, Alan H. of the Advocates for Children, 1988
        Levine, Arthur of Columbia University, 1997-1999 (Includes enclosure)
        Levine, Eliot, 2000
        Levison, Melvin E. of the City University of New York, 1988
        Levy, Harold O., chairman of the Commission on School Facilities and Maintenance Reform, 1996
        Lieber, Mimi Levin of LAR Management Consultants, 1993 (Includes enclosure)
        Littky, Dennis, 1996
        Lloyd, Kent and Diane Ramsey of the Knowledge Network, 1996
        Lloyd, Susan McIntosh, 1999-2003
        Lynch, Roberta, 1993-1995, undated (Includes letter from Meier)
        Lyne, Heidi of Mission Hill, 2003
      - M
        Maine Collaborative, 1996 (Includes enclosures)
        Maine School Administrative District, 1987
        Mandelstamm, Ann, 1998 (Includes enclosures)
        Manhattan High Schools Office of the Superintendent, 1988
        The Manhattan Institute, 1994
        Manhattanville College, 2007-2008
        Marmur, Mildred, 1988-2000 (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier)
        Maryland Association of Secondary School Principals, 1987
        Massachusetts Department of Education, 1994
        Massey, Sid, 2003
        Mather High School in Chicago, Illinois, 1994
        Mayher, Bill, 1996
        Mayo-Smith, Richmond, 1999
        McBride, Gail Covington of New Century High School and Sedona Red Rock High School, 2000 (Includes enclosure)
        McCleary, Richard, 2008
        McEntee, Grace, 1996
        McGee, Betsey, 2002-2004
        McNeil, Linda of Rice University, 2000
        McNichols, Steven, 1987
        McReynolds, David, 1996
        Meier, Daniel, 1995-1997 (Includes letter from Joan )
        Meier, Deborah, 1992-1996, undated (Letters to Susan, Joe, and Shelley) (Separate folder)
        The Merrow Report, 1994-2002 (Includes enclosure) (Separate folder)
        Metropolitan Area Educators for Social Responsibility, 1988
        Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1989
        Mid-Atlantic Equity Consortium, 1995
        Mid-Continent Regional Educational Laboratory, 1989 (Includes enclosure)
        Midwest Principals' Center, 2005
        Miletta, Maureen M., 1996
        Miller, L. Scott, 1996
        Mills College in Oakland, California, 2003
        Mills, Richard P., of the University of the State of New York, 1995
        Mind Science Foundation, 1995
        Mintz, Walter of Cumberland Associates, 1995 (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier)
        Mogulescu, Marian, 1994-1996
        Monroe, Lorraine, principal of the Frederick Douglass Academy, 1994 (Letter from Meier)
        Mooser, Etta Kralovec, 1988
        Mount Holyoke College, 1987
        Muncey, Leonna, 1996
      - N
        Nathan, Linda, 1989-2001
        The Nation, 1991-2009 (Includes letters from Meier)
        The National Academy of Education, 1993-1994
        National Association of Social Workers, 1994
        National Association of State Boards of Education, 1988
        National Center for Restructuring Education, 1994-1995 (Includes letter from Meier)
        National Council of Teachers of English, 1989
        National Education Association, 1995
        National Forum on Assessment, 1994
        National Governors' Association, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        National-Louis University, 2004
        Nehring, James, 1994 (Letter from Meier)
        The New Educator, 2004
        New Jersey Association of Teacher Educators, 1988 (Includes enclosure)
        New Jersey Department of Education, 1988
        New Jersey Office of the Governor, 1987
        New School for Social Research, 1994 (Includes letter from Meier)
        New Schools Project, 2006-2007
        New Teacher Center at the University of California, 2001
        New York Academy of Public Education, 1995
        New York City Arts in Education Roundtable, 2008
        New York City Board of Education, 1987-1995 (Includes enclosure)
        New York State Education Department, 1987-1994
        New York Stock Exchange, 1993 (Includes enclosure)
        New York Times, 2002 (Letter from Meier)
        New York University, 2005 (Includes enclosure)
        Newell, Ron, 2007-2008, undated
        Newman, Robert E., 2001-2002 (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier)
        Nickolaou, Mary Beth of the Hammond Leadership Academy, 1995-1998, undated (Includes enclosures)
        Niemeyer Series, 2009
        Nimkin, Jean, 1993
        New Press, 1994
        Noddings, Nel, acting dean of Stanford University School of Education, 1994
        North Country Schools, 2001
        North Dakota Study Group Planning Committee, 2008
        Northeastern Illinois University Chicago Teachers' Center, 1994-1995 (Includes enclosures)
        NYC M/S/T Assessment Pilot, 1994-1995 (Includes enclosure)
      - O
        Oakland University, 1996
      - P
        Page, Marilyn of Johnson State College, 1997
        Palmer, Julia R., 1994-1996 (Includes enclosures)
        Parents, 1995
        Park, Clara, undated
        Parkway South High School, 1995
        Parrott, Maryann, 1999
        Pellens, Sandra, of Lewis and Clark College, 1997
        Pelton, Claire, 1997
        Perrone, Vito, 1982, undated
        Perseus Books, 1999
        Pettus, Pamela Kent, 1994
        Phi Delta Kappa, 1987-1995
        Philips Academy in Andover, Massachusetts, ca. 1994
        Pi Lambda Theta, 2003-2004 (Includes chapter from In Schools We Trust) (Separate folder)
        Pick, Grant, undated
        Poetter, Tom S., undated
        Pomson and Deitcher, undated
        Primary Source, 2003
        Private Industry Council, 1995 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Procter Elementary School, 1994 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Professionalization of Teaching, ca. 1988
        Proshansky, Etta, 1994 (Letter from Deena Rosenberg of New York University, includes enclosures)
        Prospect Archive and Center for Education and Research, 1988
        Publication Services, 1994
        Purchase University, 1994 (Includes letter from Meier)
      - Q
        Queens College, 1988-1994
      - R
        Rainbow Research, 1993, undated (Includes enclosures)
        Ramirez, Antonio, 1987
        Ramos, Joan, 1996 (Includes enclosure)
        Ranganathan, Arvind of the University of Wisconsin-Madison, 1998-1999 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Rava, Carol, undated
        Ravitch, Diane, 1988-2008 (Includes letters from Meier) (Separate folder)
        Raywid, Mary Anne, 1987 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Reagan, Kathleen, 1999
        Reisman, Bernard of Brandeis University, 1998
        Rethinking Schools, 1994-2008 (Includes article The Revitalization of Civil Society by Michael S. Joyce and Meier's response)
        Review of Law and Social Change, 1994
        Rice University, 1988
        Rifkin, Jeff, undated
        Rivas, Michael, 1987
        River East Elementary School, 2002
        Robert, Nikia, former CPESS student, 2008
        Rockefeller Foundation, 1999
        Rohatyn, Felix, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        Rose, Mike, 1993-1996, undated (Includes letter from Meier)
        Rosenberg, Becky, 1993
        Rosenberg, Deena, 1993
        Rosnfeld, Herb, 1992
        Rosner, Jay, 2000-2001
        Rubenstein, Ernest, 1994
        Ruenzel, David, 1994
        Rural Challenge Policy Program, 1998
        Rutgers University, 1991
        Rutkowski, Joseph of Great Neck North High School, 1996-1997
      - S
        Sacramento City Unified School District, 2004
        Sadowski, Michael, 2008 (Includes foreword for Sadowski's book by Meier)
        Sage Publications, 2005
        Saletan, Rebecca, 1991
        San Jose Mercury News, 2004
        San Jose State University, 1995
        San Jose Unified School District, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        Sarason, Seymour B. of Yale University, 1996, undated (Includes enclosure, letter from Meier)
        Sato, Manabu of the University of Tokyo, 2002
        Schine, Joan, 1994
        Schippani, Michael, 1994-1995 (Includes enclosures)
        Schon, Don, 1997
        School Volunteer Program, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        Seeley, David of the College of Staten Island of the City University of New York, 1988
        Shain, Charles, 1995
        Shady Hill School in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1995
        Shaker Heights City School District in Shaker Heights, Ohio, 1994 (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier)
        Shannon, Michael J. of the Center for Design Studies, 1993 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Shapiro, Steve of Reynoldsburg High School, 1995
        Shatzkin, Karen, 1994-1995, undated
        Shefrin, Susan Russell, undated
        Shekerjian, Denise, 1987
        Shier, Carl, 1993-2005, undated (Includes enclosures, letter from Meier) (Separate folder)
        Shirley, Dennis of Rice University, 1996
        Shoreham-Wading River High School in Shoreham, New York, 1994
        Silber, John of Boston University, 1997
        Silva, Peggy, 2000
        Silver-Wolotira, Jane, 1995 (Includes enclosure)
        Siskin, Leah, 1996
        Sizer, Ted, 1984-2000 (Includes enclosures) (Separate folder)
        Sleeper, Jim, ca. 1997
        Smith, Diana of St. Anne's Belfield School, 2004
        Smith, Frank, 2000 (Includes enclosure)
        Smith, James R., 1989 (Letter from Meier)
        Smith, Lew of Fordham University, 2006
        Smith, Lucas A., 1998
        Smith, Lydia A. H., 1996-1998
        Snowden, Conrad D., 1994
        Snyder, Jon of the University of California, 2001
        Solowey, Barry, CPE teacher, 1999 (Includes enclosure)
        South Bend Community School Corporation in Southbend, Indiana, 1994
        SRI International, 1993
        St. Francis College, 1997
        Stake, Bob, 2000
        Stein, Sara, former CPESS student, 1994
        Stern, Peggy, 1988 (Includes enclosure)
        Stitham, Susan, President of the Fairbanks Education Association, 1994-1997
        Stockton High School in Stockton, Kansas, 2004-2006 (Includes enclosure, letter from Meier)
        Stoleroff, Debra, 1994
        Strong, Mike, 1997
        Suiter, Dianne, 2004 (Includes enclosure)
        Superintendents Work Conference of Columbia University, 1995
        Syracuse City School District, 1995
        Syracuse University, 2001
      - T
        Taylor, Barbara, 1996 (Includes letter from Meier)
        Taylor, Deborah F., 1997
        Teachers College Press, 1988-1992, undated (Includes foreword by Meier for book)
        Teachers College Record, 2008 (Includes materials on Antioch College)
        Thames and Hudson, 1997 (Includes enclosures)
        Thayer High School, 1994 (Includes enclosure)
        Thomas, Bruce R., 1988
        Thomas Prince School in Princeton, Massachusetts, 1999
        Tripp, Robert L., 1994-1995
        Trow, Katherine, 2000
        Tyack, David of Stanford University School of Education, 2003, undated
        Tzavaras, Roberta, 1999
      - U
        Ulster County Boces in New Paltz, New York, 1995
        United Federation of Teachers, 1988-2005
        University at Albany, 1998 (Includes enclosures) (See also: Oversize 3, folder 8)
        University Heights High School, 1988
        University of Delaware, 1995 (Includes letter from Meier)
        University of Rhode Island, 1994
        Upper Valley Teacher Institute, 2002-2008
        Urbanski, Adam, President of the Rochester Teachers Association, 1993-1994, undated (Includes enclosure, letter from Meier)
      - V
        Vander Ark, Tom, 2001-2002 (Letters from Meier)
        Verner, Kathleen, 1999 (Includes enclosure)
        Village Voice, 1996
        Vogel, Amos, 1996
      - W
        Waddell, Gary, 1997
        Walace, Vivian, undated
        Washington Post, 1994
        Washington, Ruth V., 1988
        Waterford Institute, 1994
        Weber, Lillian, 1988
        Weiner, Lois, 1987-1994
        Weintraub, Anita, 1987
        Weiss, Howard M., 1994
        Weldon, Ellena, 1997, undated
        Westbury High School, 1989
        Westinghouse Vocational High School, 1987
        Westminster Schools, 1997
        Wheelock, Anne, 2002
        White, Cheryl Stitham, principal of Morse Street School, 1997
        Whole Language Teaching Committee at Arizona State University, 1985
        Widmeyer Group, 1994
        Wiedenbeck, Barb, 1995 (Includes enclosures, letters from Meier)
        Williams, Dilafruz, 2004
        Wilson, Thomas A., 1994
        Winnetka Public Schools, 1988-1989
        Wiseman, Fred, 1993 (Letter from Meier)
        Witt, Mayra E., 2002
        Wolff, Daniel, 2008, undated
        Wood, George, 1999
        Workers Defense League, 1988
        Wyoming Seminary, 1988
      - X, Y, Z
        Yale University, 1988
        Zjawin, Dorothy, 1996
    - Letters of Reference, 1991-1993
      List of people receiving reference letters:
      Baum, Jennifer, for Clark University, 1992
      Branch, Edwina, 1992
      Chen, Jie, 1992
      Cook-Mack, Jessica, for Yale College, 1991
      Donohue, Martin, 1991
      Kanze, Bruce, 1992
      Lopez-Towey, Anna, for Marymount College Department of Education, 1993
      Malhotra, Eileen, 1992
      Maristany, Alita M., for Brown University, 1992 (Includes enclosures)
      Matos, Lucy, 1993
      Medina, Carlos, for Arizona State College of Education and Hazard Young and Associates, 1992-1993
      Minaya, Dana, 1992
      Powell, Zawadi, for Brown University, 1992
      Rudenstine, Sasha, for the Dalton School, 1993
      Russell, Sasha, for the Providence Summer Bridge Program, 1992
      Sheilton-Brevot, Marcia, for the National Association Secondary School Principals, 1994
      Stanley, Damian, for Honors College, State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1993
    - Letters with no clear name, 1994-2002, undated
    - Fan mail, 1989-2000, undated
- Writings and speeches, 1955-2009, undated (Box 5)
  - Copyright contracts, 1999 (Box 5)
  - Books, 1991-2006, undated (Box 5)
    - The Power of Their Ideas, 1991-1999, undated
      - Solicitations from publishers, 1991-1993
      - Correspondence, 1993-1999
      - Outlines, 1993, undated
      - Complete draft of book, undated, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous drafts, 1994, undated
      - Photocopied portions of The Power of Their Ideas and Democratic Schools, undated
      - Book jacket design, 1996, undated
      - Publicity, marketing, and reviews, 1995-1996
      - Reviews and student responses, 1995-2000, undated
      - Reviews and student responses, 1995-2000, undated (Box 3)
    - Will Standards Save Public Education? 1995-2001 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence, 1995-1997
      - Reviews, 2000-2001
      - Reviews, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - In Schools We Trust (Working title: The Company Kids Keep), 2000-2006, undated (Box 5)
      - Proposals and outlines, 2000-2001, undated
      - Correspondence, 2000-2001, undated
      - Revisions by Robert Stake, 2001
      - Drafts and notes, 2000-2001, undated
        - Introduction, 2001
        - Chapter 1, 2001
        - Chapter 2, 2001
        - Chapter 3, 2001 (Box 6)
        - Chapter 4, 2001
        - Chapter 5, 2001
        - Chapter 6, 2001
        - Chapter 7, 2001
        - Chapter 8, 2001
        - Chapter 9, 2001
        - Miscellaneous drafts, 2000-2001, undated, (3 folders)
        - Notes and fragments, 1998-2001, undated
        - Other writings possibly used as sources, 2000-2001, undated
      - Reviews, 2002-2003, undated
      - Reviews, 2002-2003, undated (Box 3)
      - Study group responses, 2006 (Box 6)
  - Articles, 1959-2009, undated (Box 6)
    After master copies of articles, arranged alphabetically by title of article
    - Master copies of articles, undated
      Includes articles by Meier, reviews by Meier, and articles by others.
      - Articles about Debbie/CPE/CCE-91/92, by Debbie, undated
      - Writings by Deborah Meier, undated
        Includes listing of articles by Deborah Meier
      - Items removed from pockets of the Writings by Deborah Meier binder, undated
    - ( 1999). Adolescents and Standards. 1999, undated, 1 draft, 1 speech on which article was based
    - Adolescents at School (Foreword). In Michael Sadowski (Ed.), Adolescents at School. Undated, 2 drafts
      Includes letter from Michael Sadowski and bio of Meier
    - (1975). Another Look at What's Wrong with Reading Tests. Association for Childhood Education International (pp. 32-36)., 5 printed
      See also: Writings by Deborah Meier, 1 printed
    - Approach to Reading Readiness. ca. 1967, 3 drafts
    - ( 2006, May). As Though They Owned the Place: Small Schools as Membership Communities. Phi Delta Kappan: The Professional Journal for Education, volume 87, number 9 (pp. 657-662). 2004-2006, 1 draft, 2 printed
    - ( 1998). Authenticity and Educational Change. In A. Hargreaves, A. Lieberman, M. Fullan, & D. W. Hopkins (Eds.),International Handbook of Educational Change (pp. 596-615)., 1 printed
    - (1987, Oct.). The Beautician Question: Can Secondary Education Be Progressive? In K. Jervis & A. Tobier (Eds.), Education for Democracy (pp. 68-80).
      See: Articles about Debbie/CPE/CCE-91/92, by Debbie, 1 printed; Writings removed from binder pockets, 1 printed
    - (1995, Apr.). Beyond Academics. Teacher Magazine., 2 printed
    - (1996, Sept.). The Big Benefits of Smallness. Educational Leadership, volume 54, number 1., 6 printed
    - With Ted Sizer. ( 2006). Breaking Ranks in the Middle (Foreword). Breaking Ranks in the Middle. 2005, 1 draft